<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Vlad Calin&#39;s personal page</title>
    <link>https://vladcalin.github.io/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on Vlad Calin&#39;s personal page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vladcalin.github.io/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is microservices?</title>
      <link>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/what-is-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/what-is-microservices/</guid>
      <description>The title is a reference to the famous &amp;ldquo;What is drugs?&amp;rdquo; news footage that is out there on the internet (if you don&amp;rsquo;t know it, you can view it here).
So, what is microservice?
I am sure that you heard this term and wondered why everybody is talking about it. What is it? What is it good for? What problems does this solve?
In this article I am going to write a little about this phenomenon that is supposed to change the world (and currently does).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What every Python project should have</title>
      <link>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/what-every-python-project-should-have/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/what-every-python-project-should-have/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few years, the Python programming language gained a huge popularity boost and its community grew faster than ever. With this growth, a lot of tools appeared that help the community keep things organized and accessible. In this article I am going to provide a short list of items every Python project should have in order to be accessible and maintainable.
requirements.txt Firstly, the requirements.txt file is crucial for the sanity of those who want to install your project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally I made myself a blog</title>
      <link>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/finally-i-made-myself-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vladcalin.github.io/posts/finally-i-made-myself-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>There is no secret that having a blog is no big deal. Nowadays, everybody can create and host a blog with ease. So I though&amp;hellip; why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t I have a blog?
I always wanted to write about different things that bug or incite me, write a couple of words about some interesting things I do or see other people do, offer some tips about the problems that every programmer once had, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>